<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="style.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<page title="Getting Started" uri="start.xml">
<h3>Getting Started</h3>
<p>To begin using this tutorial, there are a few steps to set up your
environment: Open up a command-line interface and run the following
command:

<code>$ <b>git clone ...</b></code>
</p>

<p>This will create a new folder called "untie" in your current
directory.  Move into this folder: 

<code>$ <b>cd untie</b></code></p>

<p>And then run the following line: 

<code>$ <b>source setup</b></code>
</p>

<p>Now, rather than seeing a "$" before every command, you'll see your
current directory like so: 

<code>~/untie$ <b>echo hello</b>
hello</code></p>

<p>Our convention, as you might have gathered, is that things that are
happening in the terminal will be put in blue code blocks.  Within
these, bold text indicates text you are supposed to type, and non-bold
text is meant to be outputted on its own.  In addition, red,
italicised text will be author's commentary and won't actually appear
in your terminal.</p>

<p>A word now about the organisation of this tutorial: Both the basic
and advanced sections are centred around a set of guided tasks, where
you will e.g. refactor a programming project, write an alarm clock
script, batch resize images, and more, and the bash skills necessary
for each of these will be explained along the way.  A quick summary of the intent
of each of the sections:

<ul>
<li><b>Basic tutorial: </b>This is meant as a decent, standalone
introduction to bash for the total beginner.  Along the way, we will
discuss also system calls, some file formats, and a few less-used bash
commands, so it should be informative for someone who is not entirely
a beginner as well.
</li>
<li><b>Advanced tutorial: </b>This is built on the foundation of the
basic tutorial and covers advanced command usage and pipelines as well
as some of the subtleties arising from an understanding of bash and,
indeed, Linux internals.  </li>
<li><b>Reference: </b>This section contains a summary of all the bash
commands and language features used in this tutorial, as well as brief
tutorials explaining certain select programs (or certain features of
these programs) that the author deemed very useful and for which a
pre-existing online tutorial was not easily located.  </li>
</ul></p>
</page>
